Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Native American Serials TAM.733
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Native American Serials
1969-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Indian Historical Society
Leonard Peltier Defense Committee
Federation of Native-Controlled Survival Schools
Native American Solidarity Committee
Oglala Sioux Community College
TAM.733
1.3 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, and 2 flat boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Native American Serials groups 54 titles relating to Native American culture originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections. The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newspapers, newsletters, and mailings distributed by Native American tribes, committees, councils, schools, and community groups in the United States between 1969-2003. The publications document news and events, addressing education, human and civil rights issues, and environmental concerns, including land and water rights. Serials are in some cases entirely dedicated to, or otherwise contain substantial coverage of, the legal justice campaign in support of imprisoned activist Leonard Peltier. Titles often contain detailed accounts of meetings and community events, and are often rich with reproductions of photographs, illustrations, and poems. A small portion of the collection originates from outside the United States, collecting titles from Vancouver, Yellowknife, and Chase, in Canada; from Brussels, Belgium; and from Salta, Argentina.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection combines serials relating to Native Americans drawn from two discrete groups of material held by the Tamiment Library. The first was a partially inventoried backlog of serials received by the library through donations, subscriptions, and in archival collections. The second group consisted of around 1,700 serials, newspapers, and magazines, organized by title as an artificial collection, referred to as Periodicals.001 or Boxed Newspapers. This material was combined, inventoried, and arranged and described in subject-based categories in 2017. The accession number associated with this collection 2017.049.
Arrangement
Material is arranged at the file level, in alphabetical order by publication title, with issues of each publication organized chronologically. Each title is listed alongside its publishing organization and city of origin, where available.
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Native American Serials groups 54 titles relating to Native American culture originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections. The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newspapers, newsletters, and mailings distributed by Native American tribes, councils, schools, community groups, legal organizations, and solidarity committees in the United States between 1969-2003. The publications provide contemporaneous coverage of news and events in local Native American communities, featuring reports on human and civil rights issues; education; and environmental concerns, including land and water rights, documenting disputes and changes in the laws governing farming and fishing. A significant portion of the collection is made up of publications specifically dedicated to or containing substantial coverage of the justice campaign supporting the exoneration of activist Leonard Peltier; these titles are mainly variations on Crazy Horse Spirit published by regional chapters of the Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, including Crazy Horse Spirit Newsletter, Crazy Horse News, Free the People, and various Peltier Update Reports. Other justice campaigns are also detailed, including legal efforts around Yvonne Wanrow, Dennis Banks, Paul Skyhorse, Richard Mohawk, and others. Additional holdings include issues of Council Fires, Indian Nation, Survival News, and several years of Wassaja. Serials in this collection contain detailed accounts of meetings and community events, and are often well-illustrated, reproducing photographs, artworks, and poems throughout. A small portion of the collection originates from outside the United States, collecting several titles from Vancouver, Yellowknife, and Chase, in Canada; from Brussels, Belgium; and from Salta, Argentina. No complete runs of publications are contained herein, and generally only a handful of issues of each publication are held.
Indians of North America.; Peltier, Leonard; American Indian Movement
- American Indian Journal: Institute for the Development of Indian Law, Washington, DC, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Americans Before Columbus: National Indian Youth Council, Albuquerque, NM, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Big Mountain News: Big Mountain Support Group, Berkeley, CA, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Big Mountain/Leonard Peltier Update Report: Big Mountain/Leonard Peltier Support Group, West Chester, PA, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bulletin: Association on American Indian Affairs, Inc., New York, NY, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Circle: Boston Indian Council, Jamaica Plain, MA, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Council Fires: Couer d'Alene Tribal Council, Plummer, ID, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Crazy Horse News: Crazy Horse News, Manderson, SD, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Crazy Horse Spirit - a special letter: Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Kansas City, KS, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Crazy Horse Spirit: Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Los Angeles, CA, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Crazy Horse Spirit": Leonard Peltier Defense Committee - L.A. Chapter, Los Angeles, CA, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Crazy Horse Spirit Update Newsletter: Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Seattle, WA, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- dxwhiide: National Coalition to Support Indian Treaties, Seattle, WA, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Eagle: Partners in the Environment, Mount Vernon, VA, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Eagle Wing Press: Eagle Wing Press, Inc., Naugatuck, CT, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Energy: Oglala Sioux Community College, Pine Ridge, SD, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Free the People: Leonard Peltier Defense Group, St. Paul, MN, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Free Yvonne Wanrow: Yvonne Wanrow Defense Committee, Seattle, WA, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Gwarth-ee-lass: Leonard Peltier Support Group, Mohegan Lake, NY, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Indian Nation: Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Chase, Canada, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Indian Reader: The Indian Reader, Strawberry Plains, TN, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Indian Resistance News: Indian Resistance News, Kansas City, KS, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Indian Voice: The Indian Voice, Vancouver, Canada, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Indigena: Indigena, Berkeley, CA, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Indigenous Thought: Committee for American Indian History, Gainesville, FL, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Justice: Native American Rights Fund, Boulder, CO, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Katuah Journal: Katuah Journal, Leicester, NC, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Lakota eyapaha: Oglala Sioux Community College, Pine Ridge, SD, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Native American Publication, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Native American Solidarity Committee newsletter: Native American Solidarity Committee, St. Paul, MN, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Native Peoples Film Festival: Oglala Sioux Community College, Pine Ridge, SD, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Native Press: Native Communications Society of the Western NWT, Yellowknife, Canada, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Newsletter: International Office of the Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Seattle, WA/Kansas City, MO/Lawrence, KS, 1984-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Newsletter: Leonard Peltier Support Group - N.Y. Chapter, Mohegan Lake, NY, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Newsletter: Native American Defense Committee, San Francisco, CA, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Oglala Nation News: Committee for Oglala Sioux Unity, Pine Ridge, SD, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Rainbow People: Gresham, OR, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Red Buffalo: State University of New York at Buffalo, Buffalo, NY, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- The Renegade: American Indian Association, Lacey, WA, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Resolution in Support of First Amendment Rights of Navajo People Facing Forced Relocation: Big Mountain Legal Offices, Flagstaff, AZ, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Resolution on the Path to Native American Indian Liberation: CPUSA/New Outlook Publishers, New York, NY, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Sota Eya Ye Yapi: Sisseton-Wahpeton Sioux Tribe of the Lake Traverse Reservation, Sisseton, SD, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Spirit of Crazy Horse - Freedom for Leonard Peltier: Leonard Peltier Support Group N.Y. Chapter, Peekskill, NY, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Spirit of Crazy Horse: Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Lawrence, KS, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Spirit of the People: Native American Solidarity Committee, Saint Paul, MN, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Survival News: Federation of Native-Controlled Survival Schools, Minneapolis, MN, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Talasi Tattler: Talasi Tattler, Houston, TX, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Talking Leaf: Indian Centers, Inc., Los Angeles, CA, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Techqua Ikachi: Hotelvilla Village in the Hopi Independent Nation, Hotelvilla, AZ, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Tribal: Tribal Life Fund, Brussels, Belgium, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Tsistsistas Press: T-Press, Lame Deer, MT, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Warpath: United Native Americans Inc., San Francisco, CA, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Wassaja: American Indian Historical Society, San Francisco, CA, 1973-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Yakima Nation review: Yakima Indian Nation, Toppenish, WA, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)